<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>http://www.gsie-seminar.org</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.gsie-seminar.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2014 09:58:35 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2014 09:58:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>

    
    
    <item>
      <title>Linguistic Proximity and Export Dynamics</title>
      <link>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/09/15/Linguistic-Proximity-and-Export-Dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/09/15/Linguistic-Proximity-and-Export-Dynamics</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Firms do not choose randomly their export market. Instead, empirical evidence suggests the existence of a geographic bias in the choice of export destination by firms. Firms tend to enter markets that are close to their existing export destinations. Chaney (2014)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; refers to this as the indirect search for new contacts, and this systematic geographic bias has been now documented by several authors (Albornoz et al. 2011&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Defever et al. 2011&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Lawless 2013&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). While the role of geography is well understood (economies of scale in the shipments, presence of a distribution network), little has been said about the linguistic (or the cultural) proximity across the firm’s various export markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I argue that linguistic proximity (a proxy for the cultural proximity of the different export markets) can explain the dynamics of entry into new markets. Cultural proximity should matter for several reasons. First, I investigate this by using French firm-level data on the exports of differentiated products and the exports of professional and business services. I look at the probability for a given firm to enter a new market, based on the characteristics this market shares with the previous firms’ export destinations. I find that conditional on geographic proximity, cultural proximity positively affects the entry of firms into new markets. I find evidence that both proximities matter more as firms export to more markets, as suggested by Chaney (2014). Finally, I find evidence that while geographic proximity matters relatively more than cultural proximity for the exporters of differentiated products, both factors matter equally when firms are exporting professional and business services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chaney, T. (2014). The network structure of international trade. American Economic Review, vol.104 (10) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albornoz, F., H. F. Calvo Pardo, G. Corcos, and E. Ornelas (2012). Sequential exporting. Journal of International Economics 88 (1), 17-31. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defever, F., B. Heid, and M. Larch (2011). Spatial exporters. CEP Discussion Papers dp1100. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawless, M. (2013). Marginal distance: Does export experience reduce firm trade costs? Open Economies Review, 1-23. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctions and Exports Deflection</title>
      <link>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/06/30/Sanctions-and-Exports-Deflection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/06/30/Sanctions-and-Exports-Deflection</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exports sanctions continue to be a tool used by countries to influence policies of other governments, and export sanctions against Iran are no exception. Over the last century, sanctions were imposed 174 times by different countries. By definition, sanctions increase export costs. However, despite the importance of export costs in shaping export patterns, we still lack understanding about how exporters behave when faced with export sanctions by some destinations. Due to an increasingly globalized economy, many alternative markets exist for an exporting country hit by sanctions. Recent research&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; explores whether and how exports deflection happened following the imposition of exports sanctions against Iran in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research uses disaggregated dataset which includes all Iranian non-oil customs records at the exporter-product-destination-value-day level for the period January 2006 to June 2011. The sample includes 1,814,146 daily transactions, 35,953 exporters, and 3,865 products classified at the HS-6 digit level. The data allows observing microeconomic adjustments. The empirical investigation for non-oil Iranian exports uncovers that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While entry (exit) rates of exporters and products decreased (increased) in destinations imposing sanctions, they increased (decreased) in destinations not imposing sanctions.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Iranian exporters enhanced their export volumes to other destinations that they were already exporting to when certain destinations imposed sanctions on Iran. -Larger and more experienced exporters were able to deflect relatively more of their exports than smaller and less experienced ones.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Exporters typically deflected first (and more of) their core-competence products as well as their homogeneous products compared to differentiated products.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Exporters reduced their product prices while deflecting exports to new destinations.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;The new destinations, which deflecting exporters targeted, are more politically-friendly with Iran.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Two-thirds of the value of Iranian non-oil exports thought to be destroyed by non-oil exports sanctions have actually been deﬂected to destinations not imposing sanctions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these findings add to the academic literature on exports costs and exports dynamics, they also contribute to the policy debate on sanctions. Sanctions may be less effective in a globalized world as exports can deflect their trade from one destination to another. The idea that one country can impose export sanctions on another may not necessarily prove effective unless the exporters from the targeted country do not have - or cannot find - compensating alternatives and new trading partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haidar, J.I. (2014): Sanctions and Exports Deflection. Mimeograph, Paris School of Economics. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; rev=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    

  </channel> 
</rss>