<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GSIE Blog</title>
    <link>http://www.gsie-seminar.org</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.gsie-seminar.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Graduate Students in International Economics blogging about their research</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 13:13:23 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 13:13:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>

    
    
    <item>
      
      <title>&rArr; RIEF Orleans 2015: XVth Doctoral Meetings in International Trade and International Finance</title>
      <link>https://sites.google.com/site/riefnetwork/rief-orleans-2015</link>
      
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2015/01/10/RIEF-Doctoral-Meetings</guid>
      
      <description>The RIEF network organizes a yearly doctoral meeting which offers the opportunity for a limited number of PhD candidates or young PhDs to present their papers before an audience of senior researchers in the field. The 2015 edition will be hosted by the University of Orleans’ department of economics (LEO-CNRS) on June 25 and 26. PhDs candidates and young PhDs should submit their papers by March 9, 2015, decisions on papers will be taken on April 24, 2015.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      
      <title>Trade and long term unemployment</title>
      <link>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/12/16/Trade-and-long-term-unemployment/</link>
      
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/12/16/Trade-and-long-term-unemployment</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is the effect of international trade on unemployment? In this paper,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Carrere2014&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Carrere2014&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; we explore the link between openness to trade and unemployment using a multi-country, multi-sector gravity model with embedded heterogeneous sector-and-country specific labour market frictions. Specifically, we introduce Diamond-Mortensen-Pissarides search-and-matching frictions, as modelled in Helpman and Itskhoki (2010),&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Helpman2010&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Helpman2010&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; into a Ricardian trade model a-la Eaton and Kortum (2002).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Eaton2002&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Eaton2002&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The resulting equilibrium allows for long-term unemployment levels, as search-and-matching frictions prevent all workers from getting employed. Key contribution of our approach is that it allows for general equilibrium effects from multiple trading partners, which would otherwise be disregarded in a two-country setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model predicts that trade liberalisation may lead to an increase in unemployment if it results in labour reallocation into sectors with higher-than-average labour market frictions. How labour is reallocated across sectors (including non-tradable) following a trade reform depends on both the exporter’s comparative advantage and the general equilibrium effect from the changes in world-wide wages, which adjust to the new trading structure. In cases where the general equilibrium effect is minimal, countries with a comparative advantage in friction-intense sectors experience a rise in unemployment, even when their welfare is increased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strength of the model is its ability to capture a wide range of effects, while most of the required data such as trade flows is readily observable. Sector-and-country specific frictions are estimated using panel data on an equilibrium unemployment identity derived from the model. The calibrated model is used to explore employment and welfare variations in a set of counter-factual exercises, and in particular to compare the impact of the potential Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership (TTIP) employment rates of US and EU countries, but also of other OCDE countries outside the TTIP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implications of this multi-country, multi-sector general equilibrium model of trade and equilibrium unemployment are several. Most importantly, we show that welfare and long-term unemployment are closely but not exactly related. Both the distinctions and the similarities between the two criteria are important. Any reform that raises aggregate demand boosts job creation, which raises wages and reduces unemployment. However, trade reforms also reallocate resources and labour across sectors, and insofar as sectors have heterogeneous labour market frictions, this reallocation also has an impact on a country’s unemployment rate. We show that, overall, trade can therefore be both employment augmenting and reducing, and the direction of this total effect depends on the relative strength of labour market frictions in the expanding sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Carrere2014&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Carrere, Céline; Grujovic, Anja and Frédéric Robert-Nicoud, 2014. “Trade and long term unemployment: A quantitative assessment.” forthcoming. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Carrere2014&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Helpman2010&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Helpman, Elhanan and Oleg Itskhoki, 2010. “Labor Market Rigidities, Trade and Unemployment”. Review of Economic Studies 77 (3), 1100-1137.  &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Helpman2010&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Eaton2002&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Eaton, Jonathan and Samuel Kortum, 2002. “Technology, Geography and Trade.” Econometrica, 70: 1741–1780. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Eaton2002&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      
      <title>Immigration and Wages Inequality in France</title>
      <link>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/12/04/Immigration-and-Wages-Inequality-in-France/</link>
      
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/12/04/Immigration-and-Wages-Inequality-in-France</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over 232 million people now reside in a country where they were not born. Immigrants thus account for 3.2% of the world’s population. In the past two decades, the fraction of the population in developed countries that is foreign-born increased from 7% in 1990 to 10% in 2010. The rise in the demographic importance of international migration led to a parallel increase in the amount of time and effort that economists devote to studying the consequences of immigration. One of the main questions raised by economists is related to the labor impact of migration in receiving economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What impact do immigrants have on the wages of native workers? Economic theory has straightforward and intuitive implications about what we should expect: immigration should reduce the wage of competing workers (who have skills similar to those of the migrants), and increase the wage of complementary workers (who have skills that complement those of immigrants). If immigrants are assumed to be less skilled than the average native worker,immigration should increase the average earnings of skilled native workers and decrease the average earnings of low-skilled native workers. If the skill distribution of immigrants is similar to that of natives, immigration should not affect the relative supply of skills and thus should not change the structure of wages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, immigration should produce losers and winners depending on the skill composition of migrants – &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; immigration redistributes wealth in the economy. In order to investigate how the skill composition of immigrants affects the wage distribution of native workers, we study the case of France. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;France is an interesting case because immigration has disproportionately increased the number of high educated workers in that country. As illustrated in Figure 1 the immigrant contribution to the supply of skills has become increasingly concentrated in the higher educational categories in France.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While 10% of the immigrant labor force was highly educated (with a college education) in 1990, this share increased to 28% in 2010. By contrast, the share of low educated immigrants (below high school) in the immigrant labor force declined substantially from 67% in 1990 to 38% in 2010. Within this specific context, we examine how immigration has affected the native wage distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1: The Educational Distribution of Immigrants over Time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/2014-11-25-Immigration-and-Wages-Inequality-in-France-img1.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Educational Distribution of Immigrants over Time&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; The Figure reports the shares of high, medium and low educated immigrants in the immigrant labor force between 1990 and 2010. The population used to compute these shares includes all immigrants participating in the labor force aged from 16 to 64, not enrolled at school and having between 1 and 40 years of labor market experience. Self-employed people are excluded from the sample.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We quantify the impact of immigration on the French wage structure by using a structural method called the ``structural skill-cell approach’’.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Borjas2003&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Borjas2003&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Ottaviano2012&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Ottaviano2012&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Structural methods impose a structure on the technology of the local labor market – &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;, they assume a specific functional form for the aggregate production function. Such assumption allows for the estimation of the complete set of factor price elasticities that determine how immigration affects the entire wage structure. Because wages in France should not adjust perfectly to immigrant-induced labor supply shifts,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Edo2013&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Edo2013&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; we allow the structural model to account for wage rigidities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1 shows our simulation results.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Our simulations indicate that immigration has, on average, no impact on the wage of natives. The table also reports the distributional effects of immigration by education. We show that the skill mix of immigrants matters in determining their impact on the wages of native workers. Since immigrants to France has been disproportionately high educated in the past two decades, the simulations indicate a drop of 1.1% in the relative wage of highly educated native workers, a 0.2% gain in the relative wage of workers in the middle of the education distribution, and an increase in the wage of low educated natives by 0.5%.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the supply shock of immigrant labor to France has been greater for high educated workers, immigration has served to reduce wage inequality between low educated and high educated workers. This result is consistent with the labor market trend to lower wage inequality experiencing by France since 1970.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Verdugo2014&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Verdugo2014&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Table 1: Simulated Wage Impact of 1990-2010 Immigrant Influx on the Wages of Natives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All Natives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medium Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;French Wages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;0.0 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;-1.1 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;0.3 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;0.5 %&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexible Wages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;0.0 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;-2.4 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;0.6 %&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1.2 %&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our results suggest that immigration has been a crucial factor in accounting for the drop in the relative wage of high educated workers in France – immigration has contributed to the reduction of wages inequality in France. By using our structural model, we quantify the contribution of immigration to the reduction of wage inequality. We find that immigration accounts for about 18% of the reduction of wage inequality between high and low educated workers in France since 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last row of Table 1 underlines the role played by wage rigidities in reducing the impact of immigration on wage inequalities. If wages in France were perfectly flexible, the positive and negative effects induced by immigration on wages would have been larger: the negative impact of immigration on the relative wage of high educated natives would have been more detrimental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to offer some guidance with respect to immigration policy, we simulate the impact of different policies with respect to migration. Our simulations show, in particular, that selective migration policies in favor of highly educated immigrants reduce wage inequality by far less than when they promote low educated immigration. We also find that these effects are larger under a scenario when I assume wages to be perfectly flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In France, the share of immigrants in the labor force climbed from 7% in 1990 to 10% in 2010. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Borjas2003&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Borjas, G. J., “The labor demand curve is downward sloping: reexamining the impact of immigration on the labor market,” The quarterly journal of economics 118 (2003), 1335–1374. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Borjas2003&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Ottaviano2012&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ottaviano, G. I. and G. Peri, “Rethinking the effects of immigration on wages,” Journal of the European Economic Association 10 (2012), 152–197. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Ottaviano2012&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Edo2013&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Edo, A., “The Impact of Immigration on Native Wages and Employment,” CES working paper No. 13-64 (2013). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Edo2013&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We provide the long-run simulation results. They assume that capital has fully adjusted to immigration. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The simulated results have a &lt;em&gt;ceteris paribus&lt;/em&gt; interpretation. The simulations yield the change in wages due to immigration only, without accounting for the other factors that may affect native wages. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Verdugo2014&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Verdugo, G., “The great compression of the French wage structure, 1969–2008,” Labour Economics 28 (2014), 131–144. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Verdugo2014&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      
      <title>Does Country Size Matter for Trade Facilitation Assistance?</title>
      <link>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/11/25/Does-Country-Size-Matter-for-Trade-Facilitation-Assistance/</link>
      
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/11/25/Does-Country-Size-Matter-for-Trade-Facilitation-Assistance</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Greater attention is now being devoted to trade facilitation measures. The 159 members of the WTO agreed during their December 2013 meeting in Bali on a Trade Facilitation Agreement. And, the European Commission, the World Bank, and other donors have just &lt;a href=&quot;http://trade.ec.europa.eu/doclib/press/index.cfm?id=1202&quot;&gt;launched&lt;/a&gt; the implementation of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wbginvestmentclimate.org/advisory-services/regulatory-simplification/trade-logistics/trade-facilitation-support-program/&quot;&gt;Trade Facilitation Support Program (TFSP)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TFSP is to help developing countries reform and modernize their border procedures. Such initiative is important as time delays at customs affect trade. Each additional day that a product is delayed prior to being shipped reduces trade by more than 1%. Put differently, each day is equivalent to a country distancing itself from its trade partners by about 70 km on average&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Djankov2010&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Djankov2010&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, there is currently a lot of variation in trade facilitation across countries. For example, while 2 documents are currently required to export a container from France, it requires 10 documents to do the same in Kazakhstan. Does country size affect trade facilitation? Is some of this cross-country variation in trade facilitation due to differences in country size? Our recent research paper, “Trade Facilitation and Country Size,”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Amin2013&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Amin2013&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; attempts to answer this question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We extend the literature beyond the conventional trade openness measures in an important way. In contrast to existing studies, we focus on micro-level trade facilitation or “inside the border” measures to define how liberal the trading regime is. We perform a precise analysis of the relationship between country size and the number of documents required to export and import, a measure of trade facilitation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three results follow. First, trade facilitation does improve as country size becomes smaller; that is, small countries perform better than large countries in terms of trade facilitation. Second, the relationship between country size and trade facilitation is non-linear. It is much stronger for the relatively small than the large countries. Third, contrary to what existing studies might suggest, the relationship between country size and trade facilitation does not appear to be driven by the fact that small countries trade more as a proportion of their gross domestic product than large countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a large body of work&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Alesina2005&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Alesina2005&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that shows that small countries are likely to benefit more from international trade or a liberal trading regime than large countries. Smallness of market limits the exploitation of economies of scale, forcing the relatively small countries to expand market size through international trade beyond their political borders. However, most of the evidence on the relationship between trade openness and country size is largely focused on measures of trade openness that include trade volume and border taxes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our paper extends these findings by showing that small countries perform better than large countries in terms of trade facilitation, too. That is, the number of documents required for export and import clearance, a measure of trade facilitation, tends to increase sharply with country size, proxied by total population. Will the TFSP start in smaller or larger countries? Time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Djankov2010&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Simeon Djankov &amp;amp; Caroline Freund &amp;amp; Cong S. Pham, 2010. “Trading on Time,” The Review of Economics and Statistics, MIT Press, vol. 92(1), pages 166-173, February. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Djankov2010&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Amin2013&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Amin, Mohammad &amp;amp; Haidar, J.I., 2013. “Trade facilitation and country size, “ Empirical Economics, Springer, vol. 47(4), pages 1441-1466. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Amin2013&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Alesina2005&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Alesina, Alberto &amp;amp; Spolaore, Enrico &amp;amp; Wacziarg, Romain, 2005. “Trade, Growth and the Size of Countries,” Handbook of Economic Growth, in: Philippe Aghion &amp;amp; Steven Durlauf (ed.), Handbook of Economic Growth, edition 1, volume 1, chapter 23, pages 1499-1542 Elsevier. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Alesina2005&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      
      <title>Linguistic Proximity and Export Dynamics</title>
      <link>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/09/15/Linguistic-Proximity-and-Export-Dynamics/</link>
      
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/09/15/Linguistic-Proximity-and-Export-Dynamics</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Firms do not choose randomly their export market. Instead, empirical evidence suggests the existence of a geographic bias in the choice of export destination by firms. Firms tend to enter markets that are close to their existing export destinations. Chaney (2014)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Chaney2014&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Chaney2014&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; refers to this as the indirect search for new contacts, and this systematic geographic bias has been now documented by several authors (Albornoz et al. 2011&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Albornoz2011&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Albornoz2011&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Defever et al. 2011&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Defever2011&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Defever2011&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Lawless 2013&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Lawless2013&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Lawless2013&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). While the role of geography is well understood (economies of scale in the shipments, presence of a distribution network), little has been said about the linguistic (or the cultural) proximity across the firm’s various export markets. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I argue that linguistic proximity (a proxy for the cultural proximity of the different export markets) 
can explain the dynamics of entry into new markets. Cultural proximity should matter for several reasons. First, I investigate this by using French firm-level data on the exports of differentiated products and the exports of professional and business services. I look at the probability for a given firm to enter a new market, based on the characteristics this market shares with the previous firms’ export destinations. I find that conditional on geographic proximity, cultural proximity positively affects the entry of firms into new markets. I find evidence that both proximities matter more as firms export to more markets, as suggested by Chaney (2014)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Chaney2014:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Chaney2014&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Finally, I find evidence that while geographic proximity matters relatively more than cultural proximity for the exporters of differentiated products, both factors matter equally when firms are exporting professional and business services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Chaney2014&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Chaney, T. (2014). The network structure of international trade. American Economic Review, vol.104 (10) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Chaney2014&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Chaney2014:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Albornoz2011&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Albornoz, F., H. F. Calvo Pardo, G. Corcos, and E. Ornelas (2012). Sequential exporting. Journal of International Economics 88 (1), 17-31. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Albornoz2011&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Defever2011&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Defever, F., B. Heid, and M. Larch (2011). Spatial exporters. CEP Discussion Papers dp1100. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Defever2011&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Lawless2013&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lawless, M. (2013). Marginal distance: Does export experience reduce firm trade costs? Open Economies Review, 1-23. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Lawless2013&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      
      <title>Sanctions and Exports Deflection</title>
      <link>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/06/30/Sanctions-and-Exports-Deflection/</link>
      
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://www.gsie-seminar.org/2014/06/30/Sanctions-and-Exports-Deflection</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exports sanctions continue to be a tool used by countries to influence policies of other governments, and export sanctions against Iran are no exception. Over the last century, sanctions were imposed 174 times by different countries. By definition, sanctions increase export costs. However, despite the importance of export costs in shaping export patterns, we still lack understanding about how exporters behave when faced with export sanctions by some destinations. Due to an increasingly globalized economy, many alternative markets exist for an exporting country hit by sanctions. Recent research&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:Haidar2014&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:Haidar2014&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; explores whether and how exports deflection happened following the imposition of exports sanctions against Iran in 2008. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research uses disaggregated dataset which includes all Iranian non-oil customs records at the exporter-product-destination-value-day level for the period January 2006 to June 2011. The sample includes 1,814,146 daily transactions, 35,953 exporters, and 3,865 products classified at the HS-6 digit level. The data allows observing microeconomic adjustments. The empirical investigation for non-oil Iranian exports uncovers that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;While entry (exit) rates of exporters and products decreased (increased) in destinations imposing sanctions, they increased (decreased) in destinations not imposing sanctions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iranian exporters enhanced their export volumes to other destinations that they were already exporting to when certain destinations imposed sanctions on Iran. 
 -Larger and more experienced exporters were able to deflect relatively more of their exports than smaller and less experienced ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exporters typically deflected first (and more of) their core-competence products as well as their homogeneous products compared to differentiated products.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exporters reduced their product prices while deflecting exports to new destinations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The new destinations, which deflecting exporters targeted, are more politically-friendly with Iran.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two-thirds of the value of Iranian non-oil exports thought to be destroyed by non-oil exports sanctions have actually been deﬂected to destinations not imposing sanctions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these findings add to the academic literature on exports costs and exports dynamics, they also contribute to the policy debate on sanctions. Sanctions may be less effective in a globalized world as exports can deflect their trade from one destination to another. The idea that one country can impose export sanctions on another may not necessarily prove effective unless the exporters from the targeted country do not have - or cannot find - compensating alternatives and new trading partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:Haidar2014&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Haidar, J.I. (2014): Sanctions and Exports Deflection. Mimeograph, Paris School of Economics. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:Haidar2014&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
    

  </channel> 
</rss>